Jodie Hearon Photograph Collection, 1953-1972, undated SC 26
Archives of African American Music and Culture
Jodie Hearon Photograph Collection
1953-1972
undated
Archives of African American Music and Culture
Hearon, Jodie
SC 26
39 photographs
Thirty-nine photographs depicting rural life in Mississippi circa 1953-1964.
Arrangement
Arranged in one series:
Series 1: Photographs
Biographical / Historical
Jodie Hearon lived and worked in farming and agriculture in Mississippi during a period of industrializationa and mechanization. Hearon and his wife, Ella, managed farming, dairy, and livestock operations. The Hearons chose to attempt a capital intensive strategy of purchasing industrial and mechanized farming equipment, while also employing local families as sharecroppers and wage-workers, to work much of the land that was previously owned by plantation-owner Palmer H. Brooks in the area of Drew, Mississippi. Photographs from the collection indicate that some or all of the family relocated to St. Louis, Missouri by the late 1960s. An interview with Jodie and Ella Hearon was conducted in Memphis, Tennessee on July 3, 1989 [see related material].
Access Restrictions
Use of time-based media materials (audio and video) may require production of listening or viewing copies.
Access to streaming audio, moving image, and full resolution digital image materials may currently be restricted to researchers who can authenticate with an IU account or who are physically present on campus. Remote streaming to individual researchers may be allowed with the completion of applicable forms.
For further information about access to online audiovisual materials, contact AAAMC staff at aaamc@indiana.edu.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Jodie Hearon in 1992.
Related Materials
See related article, "The Impact of Mechanized Farming on Black Farm Families in the Rural South: A Study of Farm Life in the Brooks Farm Community, 1940-1970," by Valerie Grimm in Agricultural History, Vol. 68, No. 2, Eli Whitney's Cotton Gin, 1793-1993: A Symposium (Spring 1994), pp. 169-1970. Contact the AAAMC for access.
Scope and Contents
This collection consists of photographs depicting rural life in Mississippi circa 1953-1964. Most of the photographs were taken at Brooks Farm or Greenwood Farm in Drew, Mississippi. Descriptions were provided by Jodie Hearon.
African American farmers; Beans--Harvesting; Grain--Harvesting
- 1. Photographs, 1953-1972, undated; 39 photographs
  - Jodie Hearon, Alex Ingram, Sonny Hill, Ms. Ella posed with mule-drawn wagons, GMC truck & 1952 Oldsmobile, 1953; PA012001; 1 Photograph 1 negative: b&w;: b&w; 5 x 8 in.;; 4 x 5 in.; They are driving four mules with a roll of corn, with one line, and Alex is driving a pair of mules that are hauling corn. Sonny is driving the GMC truck with a load of corn they are taking to the barn for the animals. The farm is on Humphrey highway in Greenwood.
    General
    Greenwood, Mississippi
  - Jodie Hearon's farmhouse and cotton field in Drew, Mississippi, 1964; PA012002; 1 Photograph 1 negative: b&w;: b&w; 3.5 x 5 in.;; 4 x 5 in.; The house had two bathrooms, four bedrooms, living room, dining room, and a kitchen. It was modern for that time- there were not a lot of houses on Brooks Farm with running water and bathrooms.
    Drew, Mississippi
  - Seven trailers hauling bails of cotton, and cotton picker [machine] in field at Brooks Farm, 1964; PA012003; 1 Photograph 1 negative: b&w;: b&w; 3.5 x 5 in.;; 4 x 5 in.; Mechanization had come to the farm by 1964.
  - Jodie Hearon standing next to 1963 Chevy pickup in front of house, 1964; PA012004; 1 Photograph 1 negative: b&w;: b&w; 3.5 x 5 in.;; 4 x 5 in.
  - Jodie Hearon standing next to 1963 Chevy pickup in front of house, close-up, 1964; PA012005; 1 Photograph: b&w; 8 x 10 in.
  - Six combines harvesting beans at Brooks Farm, 1971; PA012006; 1 Photograph: b&w; 3.5 x 4 in.
  - Jodie Hearon and Alex Angle standing in a mule-drawn wagon, 1953; PA012007; 1 Photograph 1 negative: b&w;: b&w; 5 x 7 in.;; 4 x 5 in.; 1952 GMC truck behind them is hauling corn on Greenwood Farm.
  - Ella Hearon inside the store on Greenwood Farm, with her two children standing up on the counter, 1956; PA012008; 1 Photograph 1 negative: b&w;: b&w; 3.5 x 3.5 in.;; 4 x 5 in.
  - Ella Hearon, Ms. Snail, and Henry Jones a sharecropper, inside the store on Greenwood Farm, 1956; PA012009; 1 negative: b&w; 4 x 5 in.
  - Young woman in white shorts sitting on the trunk of Jodie Hearon's son's 1957 Ford, 1960; PA012010; 1 Photograph 1 negative: b&w;: b&w; 3.5 x 3.5 in.;; 4 x 5 in.; Photo is autographed: To Jodie, [Frances Colins?]
  - Ella Hearon standing behind the counter inside the store on Greenwood Farm, 1956; PA012011; 1 negative: b&w; 4 x 5 in.
  - Jodie Hearon's horse, saddled and standing in front of grain bin and cultivator on Brooks Farm, 1965; PA012012; 1 Photograph: color; 3 x 4 in.; The grain bin is located by the bridge near headquarters.
  - Steve Hearon on combine harvesting grain on Brooks Farm, 1968; PA012013; 1 Photograph: color; 3.5 x 3.5 in.
  - Combine harvesting beans on Brooks Farm, 1967; PA012014; 1 Photograph: color; 3.5 x 3.5 in.
  - County Agent S. L. Hilton is inspecting the fields at Brooks Farm with Jodie Hearon, 1967; PA012015; 1 Photograph 1 negative: b&w;: b&w; 3.5 x 5 in.;; 4 x 5 in.; Cotton pickers are in background. At that time they only had two cotton picking machines, so also used people.
  - Combines cutting beans, operated by Jodie Hearon, J. Golden, S. Pray, and M. Pray [not recognizable], 1972; PA012016; 1 Photograph: b&w; 3.5 x 4 in.
  - Ella's aunt sitting on porch of house in St. Louis, undated; PA012017; 1 Photograph: color; 3.5 x 3.5 in.; House number is 2701.
    St. Louis, Missouri
  - Ella's aunt Sandra, uncle, and two unidentified males [possibly their sons] standing in a parking lot in St. Louis, 1967; PA012018; 1 Photograph: color; 3.5 x 5 in.; The photo was taken after they relocated to St. Louis.
  - Close-up of Jodie Hearon standing in soybean field with combine and pickup in background., 1962; PA012019; 1 Photograph 1 negative: b&w;: b&w; 3.5 x 4 in.;; 4 x 5 in.
  - Jodie Hearon with his wife and the county agent, 1964; PA012020; 1 Photograph 1 negative: b&w;: b&w; 7.5 x 10 in.;; 4 x 5 in.; Jodie Hearon with his wife and the county agent, Ms. Rainey, standing next to a 1960 Pontiac parked in the driveway of their house in Brooks Farm.
  - Group portrait taken at the Scott family reunion at the Greenwood School, 1964; PA012021; 1 negative: b&w; 4 x 5 in.
  - Cotton field on Brooks Farm with house, tractor shed, and gas tanks in the distant background, 1964; PA012022; 1 negative: b&w; 4 x 5 in.
  - Jodie Hearon standing alongside pickup truck, circa 1960s; PA012023; 1 negative: b&w; 4 x 5 in.; The door of the truck is painted: Jodie Hearon, Farmer, Ph. 158-4665, Greenwood, Miss.
  - Harvesting cotton with combines and a cotton picker on Brooks Farm, 1964; PA012024; 1 Photograph 1 negative: b&w;: b&w; 4 x 5 in.;; 4 x 5 in.; Jodie Hearon barely visible in distance.
  - Jodie Hearon hauling 16 bails of cotton in a wagon drawn by 6 mules and one line, 1957; PA012025; 1 Photograph 1 negative: b&w;: b&w; 8 x 10 in.;; 4 x 5 in.; Two more mules are drawing the back wagon; on his way to the cotton gin in Greenwood, Mississippi
  - Ella's father, Mac Cole, with grandchildren (Maxine, Christine, Ella Jean, Nathaniel, Diane, and Lillian Doris), undated; PA012026; 1 negative: b&w; 4 x 5 in.
  - Jodie Hearon's cousin, Evangelist Oliver Reeve, from Gary, Indiana, undated; PA012027; 1 Photograph 1 negative: b&w;: b&w; 8 x 10 in.;; 4 x 5 in.; Reeve is dressed in coveralls and is standing in the corner of a room holding a telephone receiver and a can of spray, inspecting the telephone.
  - Jodie Hearon with his wagons and bails of cotton in front of the Freeman Electric Gin in Greenwood, Mississippi, 1957; PA012028; 1 negative: b&w; 4 x 5 in.
  - A truck, trailer and wagon loaded with corn on Greenwood Farm, 1954; PA012029; 1 Photograph 1 negative: b&w;: b&w; 5 x 8 in.;; 4 x 5 in.; Jodie Hearon is standing in the wagon driven by two mules; Mac Cole, Sonny Hill, and Alex Ingram are standing in background in front of an Oldsmobile.
  - Head and shoulder portrait of Mac Cole standing outside dressed in his Sunday suit and white Panama style hat, undated; PA012030; 1 Photograph 1 negative: b&w;: b&w; 8 x 10 in.;; 4 x 5 in.
  - Two young girls in dresses standing in house in front of windows, undated; PA012031; 1 Photograph 1 negative: b&w;: b&w; 8 x 10 in.;; 4 x 5 in.; Girls identified as Ed Lindsey's two little daughters, Danita and her sister (name unknown).
  - Trailers of baled cotton parked in front of the Greenwood store at "Scott's place", 1954; PA012032; 1 Photograph 1 negative: b&w;: b&w; 4 x 5 in.;; 4 x 5 in.; Alex Ingram, Sonny Hill, Jodie Hearon, and John D. Thruman (sic) are standing to the right of the trailers.
  - Jodie Hearon's tractor drivers standing in field in front of a combine on Brooks Farm, 1967; PA012033; 1 Photograph 1 negative: b&w;: b&w; 3.5 x 4 in.;; 4 x 5 in.
  - Annie Robinson (Jodie Hearon's sister) and young boy [her son?], 1960; PA012034; 1 Photograph 1 negative: b&w;: b&w; 4 x 5 in.;; 4 x 5 in.; Annie Robinson (Jodie Hearon's sister) and young boy [her son?] standing in front of 1957 Ford, with Brooks Farm in background.
  - Head and shoulders portrait of a woman [unidentified], circa 1960s; PA012035; 1 Photograph 1 negative: b&w;: b&w; 7 x 5 in.;; 4 x 5 in.; Head and shoulders portrait of a woman [unidentified] wearing strapless black gown, with short hair.
  - Portrait of a baby in diapers laying on carpeted platform, undated; PA012036; 1 Photograph 1 negative: b&w;: b&w; 4 x 5 in.;; 4 x 5 in.
  - Two young boys wearing shorts, leaning against front of Cadillac, circa 1950s; PA012037; 1 Photograph 1 negative: b&w;: b&w; 4 x 5 in.;; 4 x 5 in.
  - Family portrait of a couple with their son [possibly the Hearons], circa 1950s; PA012038; 1 Photograph 1 negative: b&w;: b&w; 4 x 5 in.;; 4 x 5 in.
  - Two young men wearing suits sitting on hood of a 1957 Ford, circa 1960s; PA012039; 1 Photograph 1 negative: b&w;: b&w; 4 x 5 in.;; 4 x 5 in.; In parking lot with building [school?] in background.